本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
No dillydallying! You'll get eaten
by a Guardian Beast!
ぼたぼたするなよ
「衛獣」に食われるぞ
はい
Right!
What is it?
どうしたんですか？
Probably just my imagination...
気のせいか？
あっ
Who is it?
誰だ？
馬鹿に知らないの？
You don't know, idiot? It's Mokkania.
モッカニアさんよ
Mokkania Fluru!
モッカニア＝フルール
声がでかい
Pipe down!
The same Mokkania who, on his own,
モッカニアさんって
４年前　グインベクスの軍隊を
wiped the floor with the entire
Guinbecs army four years ago?
一人で全滅させたっていう　あの…
The one they claim might be as
strong as the Acting Director?
代行に匹敵する強さかもしれないっていう　あの…
どこに行くんだろう？
Where is he going?
Back to his room.
自分の部屋に帰るんだよ
部屋？
His room? So the rumor that he
lives in the labyrinth is...
じゃぁ　迷宮に住んでいるっていう噂は…
You three!
あなた達
I sure hear a lot of talking,
口ばかりが働いて　手がお休みしていますよ
but not a lot of working!
W-We're sorry!
す、すみません
Mokkania...
モッカニア
I'm back.
ただいま
止まる者　愚かなりし
Todomaru mono oroka narishi
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
Harari hirari yubi ni fureta
kuroi tsubasa no hitohira
诸
神字幕组
君が一つの　物語なら
Kimi ga hitotsu no monogatari nara
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
Mada ikura demo kakikaerareru
血のインクは乾かない
Chi no inku wa kawakanai
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
Dare mo shiranai hontou no bokura
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
Areta sekai kaeru no wa
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
Oimotometa no wa
Chippoke na koufuku nanka ja nai
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Tatakae todoroku kodou wo aizu ni
意のまま　進めば
Inomama susumeba yukusaki hatenai
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Aragae notauchi ikudo to yaburedo
幾度と　汚れと
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
Kizamou matotta kizuato ni yume wo
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
Umoresou na kyo no kioku
tsunageru tame ni ashita e
Episode 10
An Eccentric, a Mother, and the Black Ants' Nest
第9话 怪人
与
母亲
和
黑蚁之巢
Mr. Bear was the most fearsome
in all the forest.
熊君は森で一等大きくて怖い子です
He was always bullying Mr. Fox.
狐君はいつも苛められていました
I know who you are.
俺はお前を知っている
Then one day, Mr. Bear ordered Mr. Fox
to gather him some acorns,
その日も　団栗を持って来いって言われて困っていると
and so, he ran into Mr. Squirrel.
リス君に会えました
I know everything about you.
お前のすべてを…
He asked, "Can you give me some acorns?"
団栗をくれないかい？
And then he heard voices.
狐君が頼んでみると　どこからか声が聞こえてきます
The ants were calling out to him.
それは蟻君達でした
That's right. You're an ant, a black ant.
そうだ　お前は蟻　黒蟻だ
The ants are the weakest and
smallest in all the forest.
蟻君達は森で一番弱くて小さな生きものです
The weakest and smallest...
一番弱くて　小さな…
Mokkania, are you in there?
モッカニアさん
いるのでしょう？
Mokkania!
モッカニアさん
I'm coming in.
開けるわよ
Things are so busy with the
open house going on...
今日は開放日で忙しいの
少し手伝ってもらえないかしら？
Do you think you could help?
I'm busy, too.
僕も忙しい
そう　分かったわ
I see. Very well, then.
どうしてこんなところに…
What's this doing here?!
That's not allowed, Mokkania!
Books need to stay on the shelves.
駄目よ　モッカニアさん
「本」は書庫に仕舞わないと
This Book is very important to you, right?
これはあなたの大事な「本」なのでしょう
きちんと仕舞って置かないと
You must store it properly.
I will.
そうする
You're a good boy, Mokkania.
いい子だ　モッカニア　後は…
Next...
It's this way.
Oh, I see.
Okay, next up...
えーと　次は…
お待たせしました
Sorry to keep you waiting!
どうも
Thank you.
Thanks for your hard work.
Please have some.
ご苦労様です　さぁ　どうぞ
Oh, that sounds swell. Thank you!
ありがとう　いただきます
御馳走様でした
That hit the spot!
Excuse me. We're also looking for a Book.
あのう　私たちも「本」を探したいのですが
迷宮の中まで案内していただけないでしょうか？
Could you escort us into the labyrinth?
いいですよ
Absolutely.
The pieces are now in place.
これで駒は揃った
精が出るな
Someone's energetic today.
I hear you turned down the offer
to be an Armed Librarian.
武装司書になるのを断ったそうだなぁ
I have no interest in becoming one.
そんな事に興味はない
It's not a bad job.
悪い仕事じゃないぞ　給料もいい
It pays well, too.
It's a piece of cake as long
as things stay peaceful like this.
今日みたいな平和の日が続けば　楽なもんだ
Peace...
平和か
You don't know what happens
in the shadows.
その裏で何が起こってるか分かったもんじゃない
Even as we speak...
今こうしてる間にも
You're preaching to the choir there.
言われなくても分かってるさ
神溺教団に関する調査は続けている
We're still investigating the Church
of Drowning in God's Grace.
Good day, Acting Director.
ご苦労様です
How about you stop spying
and reveal yourself?
のぞいてないで　出てくれば
I'll show you anything you want to see.
見たいならなんでも見せてあげるわよ
The pieces are now in place.
駒は動き出しました
Pieces?
駒？
They cannot be stopped now.
もう止められません
He left. What a naive kid!
逃げちゃった
ふふ　初心な子
I don't actually know for certain.
いいや　分かっていない
But I think I've deduced the
Armed Librarians' weakness.
俺はここで過ごして
お前たち武装司書の弱点が分かったような気がする
Weakness?
弱点？
A comrade turned traitor.
仲間を裏切りだ
You've left yourselves wide open
to an attack from within.
お前たちは内部からの攻撃にたいして
なにも備えていない
What's going on, Karune?
カルネさん　どうしたんですか？
ミ、ミレポック
M- Milepoc!
So black... What is this?
黒い…これは…
あー
Karune? Karune!
カルネさん？
カルネさん
Matt!
マットさん
What is it, Milepoc?
どうした　ミレポ
I just heard Karune screaming.
I'm heading his way.
カルネさんの悲鳴が…
今現場に向かっています
Mokkania? What are you?
モッカニアさん　なにを？
Get out of here.
出て行け！
え？
Huh?
Get out of the labyrinth.
迷宮から出て行け！
Everyone needs to leave the labyrinth.
全員迷宮から出て行け！
I'll kill anyone who doesn't listen.
従わないものは　殺す
It's an insurrection!
反乱です！
Mokkania Fluru is revolting
in the fifth labyrinth!
モッカニア＝フルールが第五迷宮で反乱を起しました
反乱？
An insurrection?
ノロティ
Noloty...
Make Noloty Malche drink water.
ノロティ＝マルチェに水を飲ませる
彼女をモッカニア＝フルールの元に連れて行く
Bring her to Mokkania Fluru.
I made Noloty Malche drink water.
ノロティ＝マルチェに水を飲ませた
I brought her to Mokkania Fluru.
モッカニア＝フルールの元に連れて行った
モッカニア反乱？　一人でか？
Mokkania's revolting? By himself?!
Route 17 is packed with ants!
There are thousands!
17ルート　蟻だ　蟻の大軍だ
They're in the fourth labyrinth, too!
第四迷宮もいるぞ
Milepoc, what's going on?
ミレポックさん　どうなってるんですか？
Get everyone out. We can't counterattack.
全員撤退してください
反撃不要　全員即刻退避
Hurry and evacuate!
Milepoc, where's the Acting Director?
ミレポック　代行はどうした
She's still in the labyrinth.
まだ…迷宮の中
Can you hear me, Hamyuts Meseta?
聞こえているか？　ハミュッツ＝メセタ
What's this?
あら？
I'm going to kill you.
僕はお前を殺す
Excellent. Excellent, Mokkania.
いいわ　いいわよ　モッカニア
You might have the strength to pull it off.
あなたなら　あたしを殺せるかも
うーん
It's quieted down, huh?
静かになったわね
Most of our enemies have left.
Only one person remains.
もう敵はほとんどいなくなった
あと一人だけだから
I see.
そう
Watch out!
危ない
You're worn out, Mom.
やっぱり　おぶるよ　母さん
Mom?
母さん？
さぁ
Okay.
Take this to my room.
僕の部屋まで運べ
What is it, Mokkania?
どうしたの？　モッカニア
It's nothing. Come now.
なんでもない　さぁ
You really are a good boy, Mokkania.
本当にいい子だ　モッカニア
I reached the Acting Director
with my telepathy!
代行と「思考共有」を繋がりました
She's in the fifth library.
The ants have blocked the way out.
代行は現在　第五書庫に
蟻が通路を封じ
There appears to be no way to approach
Shlamuffen in the fourth library.
第四書庫のシュラムッフェンに近づけなそうです
Mokkania is heading toward
the Acting Director.
モッカニアさんは代行の元に向かい移動中
Also...
それから…
どうした？
What is it?
He called the woman he's with "Mom."
一緒にいる女性のことを　お母さんと呼んでいると
That doesn't make any sense.
そんなことはありえない
Why not?
なぜだ？
Mokkania's mother, Renas Fluru,
died twenty years ago.
モッカニアさんの母親　レナス＝フルールさんは
20年前に亡くなっています
What?
Then the woman with him...
じゃぁ　一緒にいる女ってのは？
...is an imposer!
偽者か？
She might be a Church of Drowning
in God's Grace spy.
たぶん　神溺教団かと
I think it's my fault.
私のせいかもしれません
Noloty?
ノロティ？
大丈夫なの？　ノロティさん
Are you okay, Noloty?
I'm fine.
平気です
I think I took that woman
into the labyrinth.
その女の人　私が迷宮に連れて行った人かも
What do you mean?
どういうこと？
They said they wanted me to take
them there to find a Book.
頼まれたんです
「本」を探したいから案内してくれって
And...
それで…
You took them into the labyrinth?!
迷宮に入れたのか？
すみませんでした
I'm so sorry! They didn't
look like bad people.
悪い人には見えなかったので
Inexcusable! That's no justification
for breaking the rules!
そんなこと　規則をやぶった理由にはならないわ！
Huh?
えっ？
It's strictly forbidden for anyone except Armed
Librarians to enter the labyrinth!
武装司書以外のものを迷宮に入れることは 禁止されている
And don't tell me you forgot, apprentice!
忘れたとは言わさんぞ　見習い！
You're lying. There's no such rule.
嘘です　そんな規則ありませんよ？
ノロティ　おぬしなにを…
Noloty! What on Earth...
アーガックス
Argax.
No way... The Church has an Argax, too?
まさか　神溺教団もアーガックスを持っている？
That means...
では…
They erased Noloty's memory of that rule
ノロティは　迷宮の規則に関する記憶を消された
and Mokkania's memories of his
mother's face and death.
モッカニアは　母親の顔とその死に関する記憶を…
And then they made Mokkania
follow that woman's instructions?
って　その偽者の言う事を聞かされてるっていうんですか？
Milepoc, tell Mokkania that
she's not his mother!
ミレポックさん　モッカニアさんに伝えてください
その母親は偽者だっと
On it.
はい
He revolted at his mother's behest?
Armed Librarians these days...
母親に言われて反乱を起すか？
とんだ武装司書がいったものだ
I've peered into Mokkania's soul before.
前にモッカニアの魂を見たことがある
His dominant trait is innocence,
相は無垢　思考は善く　望みは不変
his thoughts are of desire,
and he wishes for stability.
まるで幼い子どものようじゃったぇ
He's practically a child.
And we're supposed to accept that?
それで納得しろと？
What is it?
どうした？
That woman...
あの女の人
She looked too young to
pass for his mother.
お母さんの偽者にしては若すぎたような
Milepoc, have you made
contact with Mokkania?
ミレポック　モッカニアからの応答は？
Not yet.
まだなにも
I think we should assume that he's not
thinking properly in regards to this insurrection.
やはり正常な判断能力を失っていると考えたほうがよさそうだな
That's a good point.
ですよね
迷宮の中に一人で四年も閉じ込めてるんなんて
Locking yourself in the labyrinth for four
years doesn't exactly scream normal...
普通じゃないで…
Rithly!
リズリー
Four years ago... Wasn't that the
time of the Guinbecs revolt?
四年前？
グインべクスの反乱ですか？
I heard that Mokkania hasn't left the
labyrinth since that battle.
あの戦い以来
モッカニアさんは迷宮から出て来なくなったと聞いているわ
What happened on the battlefield?
一体なにがあったんですか？
He's just too good-natured.
奴は善良すぎたんだ
For an Armed Librarian, that is.
武装司書になるにはな
What do you mean?
どういう意味ですか？
今は話している場合ではありません
We don't have time for this!
Feekiee, go to the labyrinth's entrance.
フィーキーさんは迷宮の前に
Milepoc, telepathically ask the Acting
Director her exact location.
ミレポックさんは代行に「思考共有」で偽者の正確な位置を聞いてください
Everyone else, stay here and stand by.
他の方はここで待機を
私が行きます
I'm going in.
Mokkania.
モッカニア
That voice...
その声は？
Ireia Kitty's coming, Mokkania.
イレイア＝キティが来るぞ　モッカニア
I feel responsible for this.
私は責任を感じています
I didn't show you the proper way.
あなたを正しく導くことができなかった
あなたの心を　救えなかったことを
I didn't show you how to save your soul.
But it's not too late, Mokkania!
今からでも遅くはありません
モッカニアさん
はぁ　仕方ありません
Then I have no choice...
As is my duty as an Armed Librarian,
I will protect Bantorra Library!
私は武装司書として
このバントーラ図書館を守ります
本当に一人で行くとは…
I can't believe she went in alone.
It's not a numbers game against Mokkania.
モッカニアに数で勝負を挑んでも無駄だ
It'll only raise the number of casualties,
should things go south.
下手すりゃ　犠牲が増えるだんじゃ
Only Ireia's magic right has
a chance against him.
あいつに対抗するには　イレイアさんの魔法権利しかない
The ability to manipulate time...
時間の操作　相手の時を遅くすること
She can slow time for her opponent.
Though it depends on her
opponent's strength,
相手の力次第ですが
she can also speed up and stop
time for them as well.
時を止めることも　早めることも可能です
Though they must be within
her line of sight to work.
視界に入らなければ効果はないだな
If she can stop time for Mokkania,
she should be able to negate the ants.
モッカニアの時を止めれば　蟻の動きも止まるはずです
After that,
後は…
イレイアさんの体力か　どこまで持つか
it all depends on the extent
of Ireia's physical strength.
Impressive, old lady.
やるじゃない　お婆ちゃん
As are you, shadow lurker.
あなたもね　のぞき魔君
I apologize for before.
先ほどは失礼いたしました　改めてご挨拶を
Allow me to properly introduce myself.
I am Winkeny Bizee of the Church
of Drowning in God's Grace.
神溺教団のウィンケニー＝ビゼと申します
The pieces are in place?
Things seem to be going well for you.
駒は動き出したか　うまくいったじゃない
で　あたしに何の用？
So what do you need me for?
モッカニアがあなたを殺したら
Mokkania will kill you,
and I'll retrieve the Book you people confiscated,
that of Armed Librarian Hiza Meeken.
あなた方が押収した武装司書 ハイザ＝ミーケンの「本」をいただきたいのです
Hiza's?
ハイザの？
いいわ　分かった　あげる
No problem. It's all yours.
Thank you kindly.
ありがとうございます
Oil, huh?
石油ねえ
モッカニアの攻撃も効かないってわけだ
Mokkania's attack won't work
on you then, huh?
That's the sole reason I'm alive.
私はそのためだけに生きてきましたから
ハミュッツさん　後は　任せましたよ
Hamyuts, I leave the rest to you!
Now!
今です
Solid Swimming!
「鋼海潜行」
Feekiee can dive through metal and earth
as if he was swimming in the sea.
フィーキーは鋼や土の中でも　海のように潜れる
壁も道も関係ない　目的地まで一直線さぁ
To him, paths or walls are the same!
He can travel a straight line anywhere.
He'll capture the impostor and
make them tell us the truth!
偽者を捕まえて　真相を聞き出してやる
I'm not getting any response from Ireia.
イレイアさんから応答はありません
That can't be!
そんな
It's okay. She just stopped
time for herself, too.
心配ない　自分の時間も止めただけだ
モッカニアが動き出した時に　蟻の攻撃を受けないようにな
This way, she'll be spared any of Mokkania's
ant attacks, once his time restarts.
時間が止まってる間は外部からの干渉は受けない
While her time is stopped, she cannot
be affected by the outside world.
さすがイレイアさん　作戦大成功じゃないですか
Way to go, Ireia! So the
mission was a success!
Don't relax yet! We don't know when
Mokkania's time will restart.
安心しないで
モッカニアさんの時間がいつ動き出すのか分からないのよ
Hurry, Hamy. If you get to the
fourth library, we can win.
急げ　ハミュッ　第四書庫へ辿り着けば
勝てる
Stay still.
動くな
俺は武装司書フィーキー＝クイン
I'm Armed Librarian Feekiee Quen.
Try to resist, and I'll...
抵抗すれば　お前を…
An Armed Librarian? So you're one
of Mokkania's comrades, right?
武装司書？
では　モッカニアの味方なのですね？
Please... Save... Save Mokkania!
お願いです
モッカニアを　モッカニアを助けてください
What is it, Feekiee?
どうしたんですか？　フィーキーさん
おかしいぞ　ミレポック　この女は…
Something's not right, Milepoc.
This woman, she's...
Feekiee!
フィーキーさん
What am I gonna do with you, Feekiee?
あー　フィーキー
I can't trust you to do anything.
まったく駄目っ子ちゃんなんだから
Taiyo tojiru mae ni
Hikari wo nakushite
Mekurumeku arashi nara
Temaneku mae ni tobikomu
Dare mo itsuka owaru no deshou
Sono hi ga kureba
Mawaridasu mirai wo mezashite
Tada sore wa mou shirusarete ita to shitemo
Sagashidasu kizutsuku imi sae kono te ni
Jibunrashiku aru tame ni
A Weakling,
In order to protect the weak,
弱い者を守るため
A Weakling, the Labyrinth,
In order to protect the weak,
the weak must face one another.
弱い己と向き合う
I knew, Mother.
知っていたよ　母さん
A Weakling, the Labyrinth,
and Moving the Queen
I knew, Mother.
弱者与迷宫和皇后的棋步
太陽の色は赤じゃないってことくらい
I knew, at least, that the sun isn't red.